Marlborough, Mass. First Church records, 1704-2002.
Congregational Library & Archives
Marlborough, Mass. First Church records, 1704-2002.
RG1358
Congregational Library & Archives
1.81 Cubic Feet
(4 boxes)
The First Parish Church was organized in 1666. Shortly after the formation of the First Congregational Evangelical Society in 1833, members of the First Church voted to worship with this society, and in 1835 the First Parish and the First Evangelical Congregational Society were incorporated as the Union Society. The church was renamed the Union Church in Marlborough to reflect this new merger, and was most recently renamed in 1913 as First Church. The First Congregational Church in Marlborough records document the history of the organization, the First Parish in Marlborough, and the Union Society, including membership, pastoral care, finances, and church life. Included in the records are meeting minutes, reports, correspondence, architectural drawings, land plans, booklets, deeds, newspaper clippings, and photographs.
Breck, Robert, 1682-1731
Bucklin, Sylvester F. (Sylvester Fuller), 1784-1860
Field, Levi A. (Levi Alpheus), 1821-1859
First Church in Marlborough (Congregational) (Marlborough, Mass.)
First Congregational Church (Marlborough, Mass.)
First Evangelical Congregational Society (Marlborough, Mass.)
Goodhue, John N. (John Northend), 1810-1839
Ogden, David L. (David Longworth), 1792-1863
Packard, Asa, 1758-1843
Union Congregational Church (Marlborough, Mass.)
Union Society of Marlborough (Marlborough, Mass.)
Restrictions on Access
Access to this collection is unrestricted and open to the public.
Acquisition Information
Church and Society records were permanently loaned to the Congregational Library & Archives in December 2015 by the First Church of Marlboro, Massachusetts, as part of RG5305. Additional items permanently loaned to the Congregational Library & Archives by Rev. Kazimierz Bem.
Microfilm gifted to the Congregational Library & Archives in 1980 by the First Church of Marlboro, Massachusetts.
Accruals
Additional accruals are expected for this collection in the form of full-text transcription. There is no anticipated date for this accrual.
Historical Note
The town of Marlborough was incorporated in 1660. The First Parish Church was originally organized in 1666. In 1662, a rate of 2 pence per acre was levied upon all properties in order to raise funds to build a Meeting House; and in 1664, a rate of 3 and ¼ pence was levied to complete the building. This first Meeting House stood on the old Common, but was burnt down by Native Americans in 1676. A new Meeting House was soon erected, but did not remain in active use for long. In 1688, a larger meeting house was built near the site of the former buildings and served as a place of worship until 1809. Rev. William Brimsmead was the first minister of the town.
In December of 1804, a committee of seven members was chosen by the town to report on a petition put forth by the westerly population. The petition meant to separate the town into Eastern and Western sections. Although the committee members were in favor of the split, the town would not adopt their report. Opposing propositions from the eastern and western populations of Marlborough on where to build the new meeting house eventually resulted in the split of the town into the East and West Parishes, and a corresponding division in the church. A new meeting house was set up at Spring Hill and was opened for public service in 1806. Simultaneously, the inhabitants of the western section of Marlborough had taken steps to form a new Parish and a new meeting house. In 1808, the western part of town was incorporated as the Second Parish in Marlborough, and on the fifth of March, the West Church was organized.
In 1833, 50 members of the First Parish withdrew in order to form the First Evangelical Congregational Society. Not long after, the remaining members of the First Parish voted to form a union with the First Evangelical Society. On April 1, 1835 the First Parish and the First Evangelical Congregational Society were incorporated as the Union Society. In 1836, the East Church in Marlborough (formerly called the First Parish Church) was officially renamed the Union Church in Marlborough. In 1852, the Meeting House on Spring Hill was destroyed in a fire. A new meeting house was completed in 1853 which is still in use today. The Union Church in Marlborough was incorporated in 1891. At a meeting held on March 28, 1913, church members voted to rename the church, the First Church in Marlborough, Congregational. The parish voted to join the United Church of Christ in 1961.
The First Church in Marlborough, Congregational, UCC continues to serve the local community today.
Ministers
William Brinsmead 1666-1701
Robert Breck 1704-1731
Benjamin Kent 1733-1735
Aaron Smith 1740-1778
Asa Packard 1785-1806
Sylvester F. Bucklin 1808-1832
Charles Forbush 1833-1834
John N. Goodhue 1836-1839
George E. Day 1840-1847
David L. Ogden 1848-1850
Levi A. Field 1853-1859
George N. Anthony 1860-1869
Charles R. Treat 1870-1873
John Willard 1873-1879
Samuel E. Eastman 1880-1881
Albert F. Newton 1882-1892
William F. Stearns 1893-1895
Lincoln B. Goodrich 1896-1905
Albert H. Wheelock 1906-1916
Belvo Z. Stambaugh 1916-1920
Stanley H. Addison 1921-1928
Albert E. Beaumont 1928-1935
Alfred E. Wheeler 1942-1945
Norman C. MacLean 1954-1961
John W. Morrow 1961-1972
Zaven Dohanian 1973-1980
Jeffrey Marks, Assistant Pastor 1976-1976
Chester Dziczek, Assistant Pastor 1977
Wayne N. Pruitt 1981-1993
Mary Aberg, Associate Pastor 1989-1992
Richard L. Weber 1993-2000
Gail H. Kendrick, Associate Pastor 1994-1998
Deborah Loomis Lafond 2002-2006
M. Elizabeth Waters, Revitalization Pastor 2006-2010
Kazimierz Bem 2011–present
Scope and Contents
The records of the First Congregational Church in Marlborough include membership lists, church financial records, meeting minutes and reports, personal and church correspondence, architectural drawings, newspaper clippings, and photographs. The records document the history and function of the Congregational church and its 19th centry offshoots, the First Evangelical Society and Union Society records. Also indlucded are pastoral records, which include the personal records of important ministers in the church's history, property records, and microfilm copies of some of the oldest records.
Arrangement
This collection is organized into seven series. Within each series, volumes and folders are arranged chronologically by the start date.
Series 1: First Church records, 1704-1977
Series 2: First Parish records, 1806-1876
Series 3: First Evangelical Society records, 1833-1839
Series 4: Union Society records, 1803-1903
Series 5: Ministerial records, 1778-2002
Series 6: Architectural and Property drawings, 1866-1963
Series 7: Microfilm, 1982
Technical Requirements
To access digital user's copies via online-interface, a java-enabled web browser is required. Internet Explorer 8.x and later, Firefox 5.x and later, Opera 12 and later, Safari 5.x and later, or any version of Google Chrome are recommended.
A microfilm reader is required in order to access microform materials. One microfilm reader is available to the public upon request.
Related Materials
By First Church and Second Church of Marlborough: Boston, MA: First Church and Second Church. (1972) (17.11.1 B65.5 FIRSCB BOX 3)
Marlborough, MA: First Church of Marlborough. (1966) (17.11.1 M34.36 FIRCM)
By First Parish Church: New Marlborough, Mass. First Parish Church records, 1794-1860. (1860) (RANGE 4 SHELF 26)
By Ella A. Bigelow: Historical reminiscences of the early times in Marlborough, Massachusetts, and prominent events from 1860 to 1910: including brief allusions to many individuals, and an account of the celebration of the two hundred and fiftieth anniversary of the incorporation of the town. (1910) (T M34.3BI)
By Charles Hudson and Joseph Allen: History of the town of Marlborough, Middlesex county, Massachusetts, from its first settlement in 1657 to 1861; with a brief sketch of the town of Northborough, a genealogy of the families in Marlborough to 1800, and an account of the celebration of the two hundredth anniversary of the incorporation of the town (1862) (T M34.3H)
By Franklin P. Rice and George Maynard: Marlborough, Massachusetts, burial ground inscriptions: Old Common, Spring Hill, and Brigham cemeteries. (1908) (T M34.3)
Bibliography
Field, L. A. An Historical Sketch of the First Congregational Church in Marlborough Mass., With the Exercises at the Celebration of the Fiftieth Anniversary of Rev. Sylvester F. Bucklin's Ordination, as Pastor of Said Church. Worcester: Henry J, Howland, Printer, 1859.
Baptismal records.; Church architecture -- Designs and plans.; Church finance.; Church lands.; Church membership.; Church records and registers.; Clippings (Books, newspapers, etc.).; Marriage records.; New England's Hidden Histories.; Pews and pew rights.; Sermons, American -- Early works to 1800.; Sermons, American.; Unitarian controversy.; First Church in Marlborough (Congregational) (Marlborough, Mass.); First Congregational Church (Marlborough, Mass.); First Evangelical Congregational Society (Marlborough, Mass.); Marlborough (Mass.) -- Church history.; Union Congregational Church (Marlborough, Mass.); Union Society of Marlborough (Marlborough, Mass.)
- First Church records, 1703 1977; 1704-1977; 15 Files; (5 volumes, 10 folders)
  Scope and Contents
  This series contains 5 volumes of records for the First Church including meeting minutes and membership records. This series also 8 folders of records including sermon pamphlets, weekly sermon records, early church covenants, building, repair, expansion records for the meeting house, written histories of the church, financial records, and pew sale records.
  - First Church Records Vol. 1, 1704 1802; 1704-1802, 1852; 1852 (Box 2, Volume 1)
    Digital Copies
    These church records were digitized as part of the New England's Hidden Histories project. Digital reproductions are available to view online.
    This volume includes a list of recipients of the 1704 church covenant, lists of church members, church meeting minutes and records of votes, baptism and marriage records, lists of recipients of renewed covenants, lists of members entered into renewed full communion, and lists of church admittances.
  - First Church Records Vol. 2, 1802 1833; 1802-1833 (Box 2, Volume 2)
    This volume includes an index of the volume's records, a history of the church, baptisms, full communion recipients, baptismal covenant recipients, meeting minutes, changes in the Deacon's office, people dismissed to other churches, people received from other churches, and donations to the poor of the church.
  - Sermon pamphlets, 1730 1783; 1730-1783 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    These sermons were digitized as part of the New England's Hidden Histories project. Digital reproductions are available to view online.
    This folder contains five handwritten sermon pamphlets. The first sermon was preached by the Rev. Prentice on the occasion of the "indisposition" of the Rev. Robert Breck, who was the minister at Marlsborough in 1730, and draws upon a portion of Matthew 4:24. The second sermon was preached about 1 John 3:9 and also includes a list of dates and locations for where the sermon was preached. The third sermon does not appear to cite a bible verse. The fourth sermon was based on Joshua 24:15 and includes a list of locations and dates it was preached. The fifth sermon was based on Philippians 4:6.
    Separated Materials
    David Goodale's Book, Meliscent Warren Goodale's Sermon Book, and Two Discourses by Aaron Smith were removed from this folder and described separately.
  - First Church records and covenants, 1739 1741; 1739-1741, undated (Box 1, Folder 3)
    Existence and Location of Copies
    This folder contains two versions of the Marlborough Church Covenant and a copy of the Baptismal Covenant. Also included is a record of votes held at a church meeting regarding the pay of Abraham Williams.
    The Marlborough Church records, 1778-1785, and An Historical Sketch of the First Congregational Church, 1859, were removed from this folder and described separately.
  - Marlborough Church records, 1778 1785; 1778-1785 (Box 2, Volume 3)
    This volume contains the church records from 1778-1885 as recorded by Peter Wood, who was voted church clerk on April 29, 1778. The records include meeting minutes, records of votes, including the voting in of officers in 1778. Also included within the records are a list of members who received Full Communion, and a list of those who received their Baptismal Covenants.
  - Meeting House records, 1800 1888; 1800-1888 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - First Church records, 1806 1809; 1806-1809 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    This folder of church records includes a communication with Peter Wood, the clerk, a record of a vote to form a committee regarding the choice of Timothy Davis for "Gospel Minister", a note regarding the collection of church taxes, and a letter from the "Easterly part, or branch, of the Church of Christ in Marlborough" calling for a town meeting to settle Timothy Davis.
  - David Goodale's Book, 1806 1853; 1806-1853 (Box 1, Volume 9)
    This volume, maintained by David Goodale, is a weekly record of sermons preached "in the New Meeting House." For each mass, David provided the name of the preacher, the date, the bible verse of the sermon, and a transcription of the bible passage. There are large gaps in the records after 1809.
  - Meliscent Warren Goodale sermon book, 1839 1967; 1839-1853, 1967 (Box 1, Volume 10)
    This volume, maintained by Meliscent Warren Goodale, contains weekly records about the sermons that were preached at the First Congregational Church. For each mass, Meliscent provided the name of the preacher, the date, the bible verse of the sermon, and a short transcription of the bible passage. There are large gaps in the records after 1842. Also included is a letter which described how the volume was added to the collection.
  - Sale of Pews, 1807 1893; 1807-1893 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - First Church and West Church History, 1830 1850; 1830-1850 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Goodale Property records, 1834 1842; 1834-1842 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Monson Church Covenant, handmade envelope, facsimile of the first paper issued by Franklin, First Church Crier, 1856 1977; 1856, 1977 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Untitled Sermon Notes, June 9th (Box 1, Folder 29)
    These untitled sermon notes were found along side the Funeral Sermon for Rev. Robert Buck, but it was clear that this was a separate document so it was removed and given its own folder.
  - Funeral Sermon for Rev. Robert Buck by Rev. Nathan Stone, January 17, 1731 (Box 1, Folder 30)
- First Parish records, 1806 1876; 1806-1876; 6 Files; (3 volumes, 3 folder)
  This series contains 3 volumes of records including meeting minutes and financial records. This series also contains a folder of records for the First Parish.
  - First Parish records, 1806 1876; 1806-1876 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    This folder contains loose leaf records including handwritten copies of First Parish records, a handwritten copy of the petition to incorporate First Parish and the First Evangelical Congregational Society as the Union Society, warrants for Parish meetings, a list of Parish officers, a copy of the act of incorporation, records related to the division of church property between East and West Parishes, copies of Parish committee reports, and collectors' and treasurers' bonds.
    The Parish tax book was removed from this folder and described as a single volume.
  - First Parish records, 1808 1835; 1808-1835 (Box 1, Volume 1)
    This volume includes meeting minutes, notes of hand in the treasury, warrants issued to Parish collectors, responses of Parish collectors, prudential committee meeting minutes and reports, and reports to the auditors of the treasury. On page 39, there is a report of Joseph Williams Junior selling a pew to Samuel How.
  - First Parish Pew Sales, January 27, 1806 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Parish Tax book, 1808 (Box 1, Volume 2)
    This is a tax book created by Herman Stow, the parish collector, in 1808, which includes a list of parishioner names and their tax payments broken down by tax categories.
  - Prudential Committee of the First Parish records, 1809 1853; 1809-1853 (Box 1, Volume 3)
    This volume includes meeting minutes, accounts for the sale of meeting house pews, committee orders to treasurers, committee warrants to collectors, and Union Society meeting minutes.
  - First Parish finances of members, 1818 (Box 1, Folder 31)
- First Evangelical Society records, 1833 1839; 1833-1839; 2 Files; (1 volume, 1 folder)
  This series contains the records of the First Congregational Evangelical Society. Included in the records are correspondence with ministers, records of Rev. Forbush's relationship with the First Evangelical Society, members lists, and ecclesiastical council meeting minutes.
  - First Evangelical Congregational Society records, 1833 1834; 1833-1834 (Box 3, Volume 2)
    This volume includes an 1833 record of a First Parish meeting, an 1834 society vote to increase the 400 dollar salary of Mr. Forbush by 100 hundred dollars, an 1833 record of new members to the Evangelical Congregational Society, a list of original members to the society, and meeting minutes. Beginning on page 13 is Reverend Charles Forbush's response to the invitation to become pastor of East Church and the First Evangelical Congregational Society in 1833. Beginning on page 19 is Charles Forbush's letter dissolving his connection to the church and society in 1834.
  - First Evangelical Congregational Society records, 1833 1839; 1833-1839 (Box 1, Folder 24)
    This folder contains records related to the separation of the First Evangelical Congregational Society from the First Parish. Included within the documents are the records of multiple ecclesiastical councils called to discuss unification of the two church societies, numerous ministerial replies to calls to preach, records of early demands made to unify the church that ultimately fell through, and letters from former pastors encouraging the two church societies to reunite.
- Union Society records, 1833 1903; 1833-1903; 8 Files; (3 volumes, 5 folders)
  This series contains two volumes of records for the Union Society and a volume of records for the Prudential Committee. Also present are five folders of records. Within the records are meeting minutes, financial records, membership records, warrants to collectors and collector responses, property records, and deacon records.
  - Union Society Property records, 1833 1903; 1833-1903 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Union Society records, 1835 1852; 1835-1852 (Box 3, Volume 3)
    This volume includes meeting minutes, warrants for meetings, collectors' responses to warrants, annual meeting minutes, and a list of society members from 1837.
  - Union Society records, 1835 1892; 1835-1892 (Box 3, Volume 4)
    This volume includes an 1853 copy of the 1835 act of incorporation, warrants for meetings, collectors' responses to warrants, meeting minutes, annual meeting minutes, building committee of the Union Society reports, Prudential Committee reports, an 1885 list of contributors donating to Union Society debt relief, an 1851 newspaper clipping regarding a land dispute between the Union Society and the inhabitants of Marlborough, a member list from 1853, and reports from the committee to appraise pews. On page 74 there is a copy of Reverend George E Day's communication to the Union Church and Society from 1847. On page 96 there is a record of the Union Society establishing the Eastern Boundary of the Common. On page 132, there is a letter of acceptance from Reverend Levi A. Field from 1853. On page 133, there is a letter of acceptance from Reverend George Anthony from 1880. On page 280 there is Reverend Charles R. Trust's letter of resignation and on page 304 are the society's by laws which were adopted in 1877.
  - Formation of the Union Society, 1835 1860; 1835-1860 (Box 1, Folder 26)
    This folder contains documents related to the formation of the Union Society in Marlborough. Included in the folder are two copies of "An Act to incorporate the Union Society", lists of voters in the society for 1841 and 1842, financial records, and two statements of "Bonding" with the Union Society: one for Israel L Ames and one for John Goodale, both treasurer and collector.
  - Union Society records, 1835 1860; 1835-1860 (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Meeting House records, 1852 1867; 1852-1867 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Prudential Committee of the Union Society records, 1853 1868; 1853-1868 (Box 3, Volume 5)
    This volume includes records of donations made by members of the Union Society, meeting minutes, requests to the treasurer and collector of the union society to pay member bills, reverends' salaries and to make charges to the society. Also included are annual meeting minutes, and records off bills approved and drawn by the Prudential Committee for 1870.
  - Deacons of First Church records, 1854 1889; 1854-1889 (Box 1, Folder 20)
- Ministerial records, 1778 2002; 1778-2002; 18 Files; (12 folders, 6 volume)
  This series contains the records, history, and publications of the ministers from Marlborough. Included in the records are personal correspondence, ecclesiastical council minutes, meeting minutes, published sermons, a church history, photographs of grave sites,
  - Reverend Aaron Smith records, 1776 2002; 1778, 1964-2002 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    This ministerial record was digitized as part of the New England's Hidden Histories project. Digital reproductions are available to view online.
    This folder contains the minutes of an Ecclesiastical Council convened following the death of Rev. Aaron Smith, photographs of his grave and a transcription of the inscription on the tombstone, and two newspaper clippings: the first about Smith's house and the second about the Old Wayland Cemetery.
  - Two Discourses by Aaron Smith, 1749 (Box 1, Volume 8)
    This volume is a loosebound print publication of two sermons preached by Aaron Smith, the pastor "of the Church in Marlsborough." Both sermons are based on a passage from Lev. 26. 3-4.
    The full title reads: "Some Temporal Advantages in Keeping Covenant with GOD, Considered and Applied in Two Discourses from Lev. 26. 3, 4. Delivered June 15th 1749, Being a Day of publick Fasting, on Occasion of the extream Drought."
  - Reverend Asa Packard records, 1805 1972; 1805-1806, 1972 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    These ministerial records were digitized as part of the New England's Hidden Histories project. Digital reproductions are available to view online.
    This folder contains the records of several council meetings which were called by Rev. Asa Packard in 1805 and 1806 in response to a split in the First Church which resulted in the building of two meeting houses. Also included in the folder are photographs of his and his wife's graves as well as transcriptions of the inscriptions. There is also a newspaper clipping from 1972 about Packard and his home.
  - Reverend Sylvester Bucklin records, 1808 1971; 1808-1859, 1971 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    This folder contains a number of church communications and records related to the Rev. Sylvester Bucklin. Included in those records is his acceptance letter for the call to settle, committee correspondence, a note regarding payments, and issued warrants for parish meetings. Additionally, the folder contains are photographs of the Bucklin family grave sites and transcriptions of the inscriptions on their tomb stones.
    The Sylvester F. Bucklin Ordination Sermon, 1809, and Bucklin's Fiftieth Anniversary Sermon, 1859, were removed from this folder and described separately.
  - Sylvester F. Bucklin Ordination Sermon, 1809 (Box 1, Volume 5)